Okay, today we're going to talk about
好的，今天我們要談論
I think for modern workers
我認為對現代工作者來說
It's a must-have ability
這是必備的能力
AI fluency
AI 流暢度
Believe me
相信我
This will completely change
這將完全改變
The way you work with AI
你與 AI 的協作方式
Let's just talk about one
讓我們先談論一個
You may have a sense of pain
你可能有過某種痛點感受
Have you ever had that experience
你有過這樣的經歷嗎
Just talking to AI for a long time
長時間與 AI 對話
But it seems to be
但似乎
Can't catch the focus you want
無法抓住你想要的重點
I have such a powerful tool in my hand
我手上有這麼強大的工具
I always feel stuck when I use it
使用時總是感到卡住
That's right
沒錯
These mistakes
這些錯誤
No matter if you get some
無論你是得到了某些
根本没用的回复
完全沒用的回覆
Or you think your mouth is stupid
或者你認為自己提問很笨
I don't know
我不知道
I'm even worried about whether the information is safe
我甚至擔心信息安全
It's all about
這一切都關乎
A very fundamental problem
一個非常根本的問題
It's just an AI tool
只是 AI 工具
With real AI
與真正的 AI
There's actually a very, very big red hook in the middle
中間其實存在一個很大的鴻溝
How do you get through this red hook?
你如何跨越這個鴻溝呢
The answer is to cultivate
答案是培養
Our topic today is called
我們今天的主題叫做
AI fluency
AI 流暢度
And I have to say
而且我必須說
This is far more than just learning
這遠不只是學習
The so-called tips and tricks are so simple
所謂的技巧和竅門這麼簡單
It has to be more fundamental and stronger
它必須更加根本和強大
To put it bluntly
說白了
AI fluency is actually a set
AI 流暢度實際上是一套
A complete new method
全新的完整方法
It's not just a few tricks
不僅僅是幾個技巧
It also includes a lot of knowledge
它還包含很多知識
Movement
運動
Even values
甚至價值觀
The ultimate goal is to make us very efficient
最終目標是讓我們非常高效
Very safe and responsible
非常安全和負責任
Put AI's potential to the greatest
充分發揮 AI 的潛力
This is really very, very important
這真的非常、非常重要
What we're talking about here
我們這裡談論的是
It's not the kind of 10-to-10 tips on the internet
並不是互聯網上那種十招對十招的提示
That kind of thing might be outdated tomorrow
那種東西可能明天就過時了
What we're going to do is
我們要做的是
To build a set that can be constantly adapted
建立一套能夠不斷適應的系統
And can be used on any AI system
並且可以應用於任何 AI 系統
Core ability
核心能力
This is a long-term thinking framework
這是一個長期思維框架
Not a short-term shortcut
不是短期捷徑
Okay, so to build this thinking framework
好的，那麼要建立這個思維框架
What's the first step?
第一步是什麼？
Very simple
非常簡單
Let's understand it first
讓我們先理解一下
Between us and AI
我們和 AI 之間
There are actually three basic interactive modes
實際上有三種基本互動模式
You can ask yourself
你可以問自己
You are now using AI as a tool
你現在是將 AI 作為一個工具在使用
A partner
一個夥伴
Or an agent?
還是一個代理？
The first and most common one is automation
第一種也是最常見的是自動化
This mode is very simple
這種模式非常簡單
Think about it
想象一下
At this time, you are like a commander
此時你就像一個指揮官
You give a very clear command
你給出一個非常明確的命令
AI will help you execute
AI 會幫助你執行
For example, ask him to make this file a pick-up
例如，要求它把這個文件做成一個摘要
Or help me copy a letter
或幫我複製一封信
The goal is very clear
目標非常明確
You order it to be completed
你吩咐它完成
Then the second
然後是第二種
Let's call it really strong
我們稱之為真正的協作
At this time, the AI character is not the same
此時 AI 的角色不同
It's more like your creative partner
它更像是你的創意夥伴
Especially when the problem has no standard answer
特別是當問題沒有標準答案時
When you need brain power
當你需要腦力支持時
AI is your best companion
AI 是你最好的夥伴
Like you can think of a story character together
比如你可以一起構思故事角色
Or step by step
或者逐步
To solve a very complicated issue
解決非常複雜的問題
The last one is the agent
最後一個是代理模式
In this mode
在這個模式中
Your role has been upgraded
你的角色得到了升級
You become like a director
你變成了像導演一樣的角色
After you set the direction and game rules
在你設定方向和遊戲規則之後
AI can represent you
AI 可以代表你
You can work independently
獨立工作
The most typical example
最典型的例子
Is to let him automatically help you categorize e-mail
是讓它自動幫你分類電子郵件
Or in the game
或在遊戲中
Play a role that can interact with players in time
扮演一個能與玩家即時互動的角色
Look at this chart
看看這個圖表
Just sort these three modes very clearly
它非常清楚地區分了這三種模式
Your role will be a commander
你的角色將是指揮官
Become an assistant
變成助手
Even a director
甚至是導演
The key here is
關鍵在於
Which mode is the best
哪個模式最好
The point is
重點是
You have to know how to choose the most suitable interaction mode for different tasks
你必須知道如何為不同的任務選擇最合適的互動模式
OK
好的
We know there are three interaction modes
我們知道有三種互動模式
No matter which mode
無論哪種模式
What exactly should we do
我們到底應該做什麼
To make it smooth
才能使其順利進行
The next 4D framework
接下來的 4D 框架
Is the core skill you need to master
是你需要掌握的核心技能
These four core skills
這四項核心技能
We call them 4D
我們稱之為 4D
Sounds cool, doesn't it?
聽起來很酷，不是嗎？
They are
它們是
Delegation
委派（Delegation）
Description
描述（Description）
Determination
判斷（Determination）
And diligence
以及勤奮（Diligence）
The first D is Delegation
第一個 D 是委派
This is the first step of the strategy
這是策略的第一步
Super important
超級重要
It requires us to think clearly before we start
它要求我們在開始前清楚地思考
What is my goal this time
這次我的目標是什麼
In the whole process
在整個過程中
Which parts should be handled by me, the human expert
哪些部分應該由我這個人類專家來處理
Which parts will be more efficient for AI
哪些部分對 AI 來說會更有效率
This is a kind of wisdom about division
這是一種關於分工的智慧
OK, the second D
好的，第二個 D
Description
描述
Hey, pay attention
嘿，注意
This is not just what we usually say
這不只是我們通常說的
It's more like a deep communication
它更像是一種深度溝通
You need to tell AI about the background, upper and lower lines clearly
你需要清楚地告訴 AI 背景、上下文
And the picture and vision in your mind
以及你腦中的圖像和願景
The better you describe
你描述得越好
The more likely you are to succeed
你成功的可能性就越大
Wow, look at this example
哇，看看這個例子
Super obvious comparison
超級明顯的對比
The fuzzy requirements on the left
左邊是模糊的需求
Like making a logo for me
像是替我設計一個標誌
And the specific details of the brand title, color, target group, etc. on the right
右邊是品牌標題、顏色、目標族群等具體細節
Think about it
想想看
The result given by AI is definitely far away
AI 給出的結果肯定相差很遠
This is the core skill
這是核心技能
The third D
第三個 D
Description
評估
OK, when AI gives you something
好的，當 AI 給你一些東西時
It's your turn to be professional
輪到你展現專業性
You can't accept the whole thing
你不能全盤接受
But like a general editor
而是像一個總編輯一樣
Use your professional knowledge and critical thinking
運用你的專業知識和批判性思維
To evaluate what AI gives you
評估 AI 給你的東西
What is useful and what is garbage
什麼是有用的，什麼是垃圾
Then divide them
然後將它們分開
So when you are describing
所以當你在描述時
You need to have a list in your mind
你需要在腦海中有一份清單
Keep asking yourself a few questions
不斷問自己幾個問題
Hey, the data given by AI
嘿，AI 給出的數據
Have you checked the facts?
你有檢查過事實嗎？
Does its logic work?
它的邏輯是否行得通？
Does it give me any advice
它給我任何建議嗎？
Is there any conflict with my original values or goals?
是否與我的原始價值觀或目標有衝突？
The most important thing is
最重要的是
Can this thing really help me solve the problem?
這個東西能真正幫我解決問題嗎？
So you see, describing and distinguishing
所以你看，描述和區分
These two things
這兩件事
Form a very, very strong cycle of the right side
形成了右側非常、非常強大的循環
We propose a demand, which is description
我們提出一個需求，這就是描述
Then evaluate the result, which is discrimination
然後評估結果，這就是區分
Then follow the evaluation results
然後根據評估結果
To evaluate the results
去評估結果
OK, the last D is
好的，最後的D是
This sounds a bit serious
這聽起來有點嚴肅
But it's a sense of responsibility as a user
但這是作為使用者的責任感
No matter how much AI has helped you
無論AI幫助了你多少
The final product
最終產品
You have to take full responsibility
你必須承擔全部責任
This includes the correctness of the information you want to check
這包括你想要檢查的信息的正確性
The privacy of the data protection
數據保護的隱私
And ensure that the entire process is fair and transparent
並確保整個過程是公平和透明的
Can be reviewed
可以被審查
So when we put the three interactive modes I mentioned earlier
所以當我們將我之前提到的三種互動模式
And this 4D frame
和這個4D框架
Combined together
結合在一起
You will find a clear path to an AI assistant
你會發現一條通往AI助手的清晰路徑
Just appeared
剛剛出現了
I think this sentence is too good
我認為這句話太好了
The key is really here
關鍵確實在這裡
The 4D frame we learned today
我們今天學到的4D框架
It is not bound to any specific AI tool
它不受限於任何特定的AI工具
It is a basic, fundamental skill
它是一項基本的、根本的技能
As long as you master it
只要你掌握了它
No matter how the technology changes in the future
無論未來技術如何變化
You can adapt and grow with it
你都能適應並與它一起成長
Through the real strategy of mastering the tail
通過掌握末尾的真實策略
Description of art
描述的藝術
The wisdom of discrimination
區分的智慧
And the sense of responsibility
和責任感
You can start from a person who only orders
你可以從一個只會下單的人
Really transformed into an expert who can cooperate with AI
真正轉變成能與AI協作的專家
Now it's your turn to think about it
現在輪到你思考了
Next time when you open the AI tool
下次當你打開AI工具時
How will you apply this 4D frame
你將如何應用這個4D框架